<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Edited by John Mattsson for use with xml2rfc -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>


<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mglt-ipsecme-ikev2-diet-esp-extension-00" ipr="trust200902">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="ESP IKEv2">Internet Key Exchange version 2 (IKEv2) extension for the ESP Header Compression (EHC) Strategy </title>

        <author fullname="Daniel Migault" initials="D." surname="Migault">
            <organization>Ericsson</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>8275 Trans Canada Route</street>
                    <city>Saint-Laurent, QC H4S</city>
                    <country>Canada</country>
                </postal>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>daniel.migault@ericsson.com</email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Tobias Guggemos" initials="T." surname="Guggemos">
            <organization>LMU Munich</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Oettingenstr. 67</street>
                    <city>80538 Munich</city>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>guggemos@mnm-team.org</email>
                <uri>www.mnm-team.org/~guggemos</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <area>Security</area>

        <workgroup>ipsecme</workgroup>

<abstract> 
	
<t>ESP Header Compression (EHC) reduces the ESP overhead by compressing
ESP fields. Compression results from a coordination of various EHC
Rules designed as EHC Strategies. An EHC Strategy may require to be
configured with some configuration parameters.</t>

<t>When a Security Association (SA) is enabling EHC, the two peers need to agree
which EHC Strategy is applied as well as its associated
configuration parameters.</t>

<t>This document describes an extension of IKEv2 that enables two peers
to agree on a specific EHC Strategy as well as its associated
configuration parameters.</t> 

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Requirements notation">
            
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">
        
<t>This section defines terms and acronyms used in this document.
            
<list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
                
<t hangText="- EHC Strategy : "> EHC Strategy is a
generic term defined in <xref target="I-D.mglt-ipsecme-diet-esp"/> that
defines the way EHC Rules are coordinated.</t>
                
<t hangText="- Designated EHC Strategy: "> the specific EHC Strategy
agreed between the two peers. <xref target="I-D.mglt-ipsecme-diet-esp"/>
defines Diet-ESP as an EHC Strategy and other may be defined in the
future. This document only considers Diet-ESP but provides negotiation
mechanisms so future EHC Strategies may also be negotiated. New EHC
Strategies will require to register the necessary associated EHC
Strategy Configuration Parameters.  This will typically include a
specific designation as well as specific configuration parameters. The
parameters are designated as EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter
(Parameter)</t>
                
<t hangText="- EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter (Parameter): ">
describes the configuration parameters associated to a specific EHC
Strategy. The Parameters includes the EHC Strategy as well as
configuration parameters.</t>
                
<t hangText="- EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter Attributes
(Attribute): "> designates the necessary attributes associated to each
Parameter exchanged in order to agree on the EHC Strategy Configuration
Parameter. This document considers two type of attributes: the Range
Attribute that indicates a range for a given Parameter, and the Value
Attribute that indicates a fixed value associated to a Parameter.</t>

<t hangText="- Range Attribute: "> the payload that indicates a
supported range of values on an specific EHC Strategy Configuration
Parameter. In this document, all Parameters are associated a specific
Range Attribute.</t>
              
<t hangText="- Value Attribute:"> the payload that indicates a value of
an specific EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter. In this document, all
Parameters are associated a specific Value Payload.</t> 
            
</list></t>
        
</section>
        
<section title="Introduction">

<t>ESP Header Compression (EHC) <xref
target="I-D.mglt-ipsecme-diet-esp"/> reduces the ESP overhead by
compressing ESP fields. Compression results from a coordination of
various EHC Rules performed by the EHC Strategy. The EHC Strategy may
require to be configured with some configuration parameters designated
as EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter (or simply Parameter). </t>

<t>When a Security Association (SA) is enabling EHC the two peers needs to agree
which EHC Strategy strategy is applied as well as its associated
configuration parameters.</t>

<t>This document describes an extension of IKEv2 that enables two peers
to agree on a specific EHC Strategy as well as its associated
Parameters. </t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Overview">

<t>EHC Strategies are configured on a per-SA basis and need to be agreed
between the two peers. An EHC Strategy is agreed when peers have agreed
on the EHC Strategy as well as its associated Parameters.</t>

<t>For example,  <xref target="I-D.mglt-ipsecme-diet-esp"/> defines an
EHC Strategy called as Diet-ESP which requires the following
Parameters to be set: udplite_coverage, tcp_lsb, tcp_options,
tcp_urgent, esp_sn_lsb, esp_spi_lsb, esp_align.</t>
  
<t>The negotiation of the EHC Strategy as well as its
Parameters is performed via the EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload
exchange.</t>

<t>When the initiator is willing to negotiate an EHC Strategy for a
given SA, it sends a single EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload in its
IKE_AUTH and CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange. This Notify Payload indicates the
support to negotiate EHC Strategies. In addition, the Notify Payload MAY
indicates with a Range Attribute, the supported values for each
Parameter, including the Designated EHC Strategy. If the initiator does
not have any restriction regarding a specific Parameter, there is no
need to provide an Range Value associated to that Parameter.  </t>

<t>Currently, the only defined EHC Strategy is Diet-ESP, and the
EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload indicates the support for Diet-ESP
unless Diet-ESP is explicitly excluded by the Range Attribute. In the
future, when other EHC Strategies will be defined, the support of that
new Designated EHC Strategy will need to be explicitly announced with
its associated Range Attribute. Other Parameters MAY also have their own
associated Range Attribute. Note that if multiple EHC Strategies that
share a given Parameter, the Range Attribute is applied for all
designated EHC Strategies. In other words, it is not possible to have a
given Parameter associated with different values depending on the EHC
Strategy.</t>

<t>Upon receiving the IKE_AUTH and CREATE_CHILD_SA with a
EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload, a receiver that does not support
this extension or that is not willing to activate EHC ignores the Notify
Payload and the negotiation continues as a standard ESP negotiation. If
the responder supports EHC Strategy negotiation and chooses to apply a
supported EHC Strategy to the negotiated SA, it reads all Range
Attributes and selects a Designated EHC Strategy as well as specific
values for each Parameter associated to the Designated EHC Strategy.
The responder enables EHC for the negotiated SA and responds with an
EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload which indicates the selected
Parameters' values using Value Attributes. The responder MAY send a
Value Attribute that corresponds to all selected Parameters. On the
other hand, the responder MAY also send only the Value Attribute of
Parameters whose value differs from the default value. In fact each EHC
Strategy defines default values for each Parameters.</t>

<t>In some cases, the supported values provided by the initiator may not
match those of the responder, and so EHC cannot be activated. The
responder may want to indicate the supported range provided by the
initiator were not acceptable by responding with a
EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER. The initiator MAY carry Range
Attributes in order to indicates what it supports. </t>

<t>Upon receiving a EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload back, the
initiator reads the Value Attributes and checks the Parameters match the
supported range. The initiator may configure the EHC Strategy with the
provided parameters or abort the negotiation with a Delete Payload as
specified in section 3.11 of <xref target="RFC7296"/>.</t>

<t>Upon receiving a EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER Notify Payload,
the initiator may use the regular ESP or delete the SA. When the SA is
deleted, the initiator is expected to restart a negotiation providing
contraints that respect those of the responder.</t>  


             <figure title="Protocol Overview">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
Initiator                         Responder
-------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SA, KEi, Ni -->
                             <-- HDR, SA, KEr, Nr
HDR, SK {IDi, AUTH,
     SA, TSi, TSr,
     N(EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED)} -->
                             <-- HDR, SK {IDr, AUTH,
                                      SA, TSi, TSr,
                                      N(EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED)}
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>

</section>

<section title="Notify Payload">


<t><xref target="fig-notify-payload"/> illustrates the Notify Payload
packet format as described in section 3.10 of <xref target="RFC7296"/>,
used for both EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED and EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER
Notify Payloads.</t>
 
<t>Both EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED and EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER Notify
Payloads are used during the IKE_AUTH and CREATE_CHILD_SA. The sender is
expected to send only a single payload. When multiple payloads are
received, the receiver MAY consider the first one and MUST ignore the
remaining ones.</t>

             <figure title="Notify Payload" anchor="fig-notify-payload">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
                         1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Next Payload  |C|  RESERVED   |         Payload Length        |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |  Protocol ID  |   SPI Size    |      Notify Message Type      |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>

<t>The fields Next Payload, Critical Bit, RESERVED, and Payload Length
are defined in <xref target="RFC7296"/>.  Specific fields defined in this
document are:

        <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
                <t hangText="- Protocol ID (1 octet):"> set to zero.</t>
                <t hangText="- SPI Size (1 octet):"> set to zero.</t>
		<t hangText="- Notify Message Type (2 octets):">
Specifies the type of notification message. It is set to &lt;TBA1 by
IANA&gt; for the EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED and &lt;TBA2 by IANA&gt;.for
EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER.</t>
        </list></t>

<section title="EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload">

<t>The EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED Notify Payload indicates the supported EHC
Strategies.</t>

<t>When sent by the initiator, it MAY contain Range Attributes (see
<xref target="sec-range-attribute"/>). A responder not
understanding a Range Attribute MUST ignore it. This is intended to ease
the negotiation of new EHC Strategies with new Parameters.  It is its
responsibility to understand the Parameters associated to the negotiated
EHC Strategy.</t>

<t>When sent by the responder, it MAY contain Value Attributes (see
<xref target="sec-value-attribute"/>). An initiator not understanding a
Value Payload MUST NOT create the SA and SHOULD send a Delete Payload to
the responder  as described in section 3.11 of <xref
target="RFC7296"/>.</t>  

</section>

<section title="EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER Notify Payload">

<t>The EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER Notify Payload indicates the
responder supports of EHC Strategy negotiation but was not able to
configure it due to the constraints provided by the initiator. The
responder MAY insert Range Attributes (see <xref
target="sec-range-attribute"/>) to inform the initiator of its
supported ranges.</t>

<t>The responder has configured the SA without enabling the EHC. Upon
receiving the Notify Payload, the initiator MAY accept the SA without
EHC. It MAY also Delete the SA as described in section 3.11 of <xref
target="RFC7296"/> and renegotiate the SA, considering the responder's
supported ranges.</t>


</section>

</section>

<section title="EHC Strategy Configuration Parameters">

<t>This document only considers Diet-ESP, which requires the following
Parameters to be agreed by the two peers: esp_align, esp_spi_lsb,
esp_spi_sn, tcp_urgent, tcp_options, tcp_lsb, udplite_coverage. In
addition, in order to enable future EHC Strategies, the following
parameter has been introduce to designate the agreed EHC Strategy:
ehc_strategy. <xref target="fig-param-values"/> lists these Parameters
with description and associated values.</t>          

<t>In addition, each of these parameter is associated to a default
value. The default value is considered unless other values are specified
by the responder. The associated default value is specified in <xref
target="fig-param-values"/>.</t>

<figure title="Parameter Values" anchor="fig-param-values">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
Parameter        Value    Description                   Default   
---------------------------------------------------------------
ehc_strategy     0        Diet-ESP                          *
                 1-127    Unassigned         
                 128-255  Private Used
esp_align        0        8 bit alignment                   *
                 1        16 bit alignment
                 2        32 bit alignment
                 3-255    Unassigned
esp_spi_lsb      0        0 bit length SPI                  *
                 1        8 bit length SPI  
                 2        16 bit length SPI  
                 3        24 bit length SPI  
                 4        24 bit length SPI  
                 5-255    Unassigned
esp_spi_sn       0        0 bit length SPI                  *
                 1        8 bit length SN  
                 2        16 bit length SN  
                 3        24 bit length SN  
                 4        24 bit length SN
                 5-255    Unassigned
tcp_urgent       0        Urgent pointer field compressed 
                 1        Urgent pointer field uncompressed *
                 2-255    Unassigned
tcp_options      0        TCP option field compressed
                 1        TCP option field uncompressed     *
                 2-255    Unassigned
tcp_lsb          0        0 bit length SN   
                 1        8 bit length SN  
                 2        16 bit length SN  
                 3        24 bit length SN  
                 4        24 bit length SN  
                 5-255    Unassigned
udplite_coverage 0        Coverage is UDP Length
                 8-65535  Coverage 8 (the UDP-Lite Header)
                 1-7      Unassigned
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>

</section>

<section title="EHC Strategy Configuration Parameter Attributes">

<t>For each of these Parameters, the initiator or responder may indicate
acceptable values of these Parameters. Such constraints are expressed
with the Range Attributes. Each Parameters has its corresponding payload
which carries the minimum and maximum acceptable values associated to
the parameters (see <xref target="sec-range-attribute"/>).</t>

<t>Similarly, for each of these Parameters, the responder needs to be
able to provide the selected value associated to the Parameter. Each of
these Parameters' value can be expressed by via the Value Attribute.
Each parameter has a corresponding payload which carries the associated
value (see <xref target="sec-value-attribute"/>).</t>

<t>The Range Attribute and Value Attribute use the format of the
Transform Attribute of section 3.3.5 of <xref target="RFC7296"/>
represented in <xref target="fig-attributes-payload"/>.  The fields are
described in <xref target="RFC7296"/>.</t>

             <figure title="Parameter Attributes" anchor="fig-attributes-payload">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
                        1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |A|       Attribute Type        |    AF=0  Attribute Length     |
   |F|                             |    AF=1  Attribute Value      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                   AF=0  Attribute Data                        |
   |                   AF=1  Not Transmitted                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>

<t>The document considers only the TLV format so AF = 0 with the
Parameter Types defined in <xref target="fig-att-type"/> and
acceptable and default Parameter's Values are defined in <xref
target="fig-param-values"/>.</t>
  
             <figure title="Attribute Type" anchor="fig-att-type">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
Attribute Type                      Value   Associated Parameter
---------------------------------------------------------------- 
EHC Designated Strategy Range        0       ehc_strategy          
ESP Alignment Range                  1       esp_align
ESP LSB SPI Range                    2       esp_spi_lsb    
ESP LSB SN Range                     3       esp_spi_sn
TCP Urgent Range                     4       tcp_urgent
TCP Options Range                    5       tcp_options 
TCP LSB Range                        6       tcp_lsb 
UDP-Lite Coverage Range              7       udplite_coverage           
Unassigned                          8-63     
EHC Designated Strategy Value       64      ehc_strategy      
ESP Alignment Value                 65      esp_align
ESP LSB SPI Value                   66      esp_spi_lsb
ESP LSB SN Value                    67      esp_spi_sn
TCP Urgent Value                    68      tcp_urgent
TCP Options Value                   69      tcp_options
TCP LSB Value                       70      tcp_lsb
UDP-Lite Coverage Value             71      udplite_coverage
Unassigned                          72-99 
Private Use                         100-127           
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>



<section title="Range Attribute" anchor="sec-range-attribute">

<t>The Parameter's value of ehc_strategy, esp_align, esp_spi_lsb, esp_sn_lsb,
tcp_urgent, tcp_options, tcp_lsb and udplite_coverage is coded on 1 byte, so the
Attribute Data of the Range Attribute is 2 byte long and the Attribute Length is
set to 4. The first byte indicates the minimal acceptable value, while the
second byte indicates the maximal value.</t>

<t>Similarly, udplight_coverage is coded on 2 bytes, so the Attribute Data of
the Range Attribute is 4 byte long, and Attribute Length is set to 6.</t>

</section>

<section title="Value Attribute" anchor="sec-value-attribute">

<t>The Parameters ehc_strategy, esp_align, esp_spi_lsb, esp_sn_lsb, tcp_urgent,
tcp_options and tcp_lsb the Attribute Data is codes on 1 byte, and Attribute
Length is set to 3.</t>

<t>Similarly, udplight_coverage is coded on 2 bytes, so the Attribute Data of
the Value Attribute is 2 byte long and the Attribute Length is set to 4.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>IANA is requested to allocate two values in the IKEv2 Notify Message
Types - Status Types registry:</t>

        <figure>
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
IKEv2 Notify Message Types - Status Types
-----------------------------------------
EHC_STRATEGY_SUPPORTED               TBA1
EHC_STRATEGY_UNACCEPTABLE_PARAMETER  TBA2
                 ]]></artwork>
            </figure>

             <figure title="Attribute Type">
                 <artwork><![CDATA[
Attribute Type                      Value   
-------------------------------------------- 
EHC Designated Strategy Range 0            
ESP Alignment Range           1       
ESP LSB SPI Range             2       
ESP LSB SN Range              3       
TCP Urgent Range              4       
TCP Options Range             5       
TCP LSB Range                 6       
UDP-Lite Coverage Range       7                 
Unassigned                          8-42
Private Use                         43-63    
EHC Designated Strategy Value       64       
ESP Alignment Value                 65      
ESP LSB SPI Value                   66      
ESP LSB SN Value                    67      
TCP Urgent Value                    68      
TCP Options Value                   69      
TCP LSB Value                       70      
UDP-Lite Coverage Value             71      
Unassigned                          72-116 
Private Use                         117-127           
                 ]]></artwork>
             </figure>

        </section>

        <section anchor="sec-security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
        </section>

    </middle>
 
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7296.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.mglt-ipsecme-diet-esp"?>
       </references>

<!--
        <references title="Informational References">
                   <reference anchor="fit-iot-lab" target="https://www.iot-lab.info">
            <front>
                <title>Future Internet of Things (FIT) IoT-LAB</title>
                <author/>
                <date/>
            </front>
        </reference>

       </references>
-->

    </back>
</rfc>

